

#### COMPUTER SCIENCE P.H.D CANDIDATE INTERESTED IN THE APPLICATION OF NLP METHODS IN COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENCE

Unter Sachsenhausen 6-8, Cologne 50667, Germany

🛘 +49(221)47694-253 | 🗖 Indira.Sen@gesis,org | 🌴 https://indiiigo.github.io/ | 🗖 Indiiigo | 💆 @indiiigosky | Google Scholar

## Research Interests \_

I'm interested in improving the measurement of psychosocial constructs, including political and prejudicial attitudes and behaviors, from digital trace data using mixed methods and natural language processing. My research aims to illuminate and characterize the potentials, pitfalls, and consequences of understanding such attitudes from unobtrusive digital traces.

## Education

## **RWTH-Aachen and GESIS - Leibnitz Institute for Social Sciences**

Cologne, Germany

P.H.D IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

ADVISOR: PROF. CLAUDIA WAGNER

Oct, 2018 - Oct, 2023 (exp)

### Indraprastha Institute of Information Technology (IIIT-D)

New Delhi, India

M.S IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Aug, 2015 - Dec, 2017

ADVISOR: PROF. PONNURANGAM KUMARAGURU (PK)

**GPA:** 8.67/10

#### **Vellore Institute of Technology (VIT)**

Vellore, India

B.S IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Jul, 2010 - May, 2014

**GPA:** 9.1/10

## Honors & Awards \_\_\_\_\_

2022	Research Award for Interdepartmental Collaboration, for interdisciplinary research collaborations	GESIS
2021	Summer Intern Award for Outstanding Innovation, Nokia Bell Labs	Cambridge, UK / virtual
2021-	Best Reviewer Award, ICWSM (2021, 20222, 2023), The WebConf (2023)	
2023	<b>Dest Reviewer Award</b> , 16W3M (2021, 20222, 2023), The Webeshi (2023)	
2020	Travel Grant for attending EMNLP,	virtual
2020	Selected for SAGE Text-Mining Fellowship, SAGE, Ocean	London, UK (virtual)
2020	Selected as Facilitator for the Alan Turing Institute Data Study Group, 2 week hackathon where we	
	worked with an Industry partner (CatsAI) to deploy explainable AI predictions	virtual
2020	Travel Grant, For attending FAT* 2020	Barcelona, Spain
2019	Travel Grant, For attending Summer Institute in Computational Social Science (SICCS), Germany	Bamberg, Germany
2017	TA Excellence Award, Foundations of Computer Security	IIIT-Delhi, India
2017	Accepted to Summer@EPFL, One of 60 interns selected out of 2000 applications	EPFL, Switzerland
2015-		WED 11: 1 1:
2016	<b>Dean's Merit List</b> , For Academic Performance	IIIT-Delhi, India
2015	GATE Scholarship, Scholarship for Master's Studies	
2011-	Marit Cabalayahin Fay Outstanding Acadaysis Ashioyayaant	1//T 1/e !!
2014	Merit Scholarship, For Outstanding Academic Achievement	VIT, Vellore

## Publications \_\_\_\_\_

#### **Journal Articles**

# Insider Stories: Analyzing Internal Sustainability Efforts of Major US Companies from Online Reviews.

2023

INDIRA SEN, DANIELE QUERCIA, LICIA CAPRA, MATTEO MONTECCHI, AND SANJA ŠĆEPANOVIĆ. HUMANITIES AND SOCIAL SCIENCES COMMUNICATIONS 10, NO. 1 (2023): 1-9.

JULY 11, 2023 INDIRA SEN · CV 1

Depression at Work: Exploring Depression in Major US Companies from Online Reviews.  Indira Sen, Daniele Quercia, Marios Constantinides, Matteo Montecchi, Licia Capra, Sanja Scepanovic, and Renzo Bianchi.	2022
PROCEEDINGS OF THE ACM ON HUMAN-COMPUTER INTERACTION. TO BE PRESENTED AT THE 25TH ACM CONFERENCE ON COMPUTER-SUPPORTED COOPERATIVE WORK AND SOCIAL COMPUTING (CSCW)	
Visualizing Internal Sustainability Efforts in Big Companies.  Chiara Ceccarini, Edyta Paulina Bogucka, Indira Sen, Marios Constantinides, Catia Prandi, and Daniele Quercia.  IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications	2022
A Total Error Framework for Digital Traces of Human Behavior on Online Platforms Indira Sen, Fabian Floeck, Katrin Weller, Bernd Weiss, and Claudia Wagner. Public Opinion Quarterly	2021
Conference Articles	
Counterfactually Augmented Data and Unintended Bias: The Case of Sexism and Hate Speech Detection Indira Sen, Mattia Samory, Claudia Wagner and Isabelle Augenstein.	2022 short paper
ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF THE NORTH AMERICAN CHAPTER OF THE ASSOCIATION FOR COMPUTATIONAL LINGUISTICS (NAACL)	
How Does Counterfactually Augmented Data Impact Models for Social Computing Constructs?	2021
Indira Sen, Mattia Samory, Fabian Floeck, Claudia Wagner and Isabelle Augenstein.  Conference on Empirical Methods on Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)	
"Call me sexist, but": Revisiting Sexism Detection Using Psychological Scales and Adversarial Samples	2021
Mattia Samory, <b>Indira Sen</b> , Julian Kohne, Fabian Floeck, and Claudia Wagner. International Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM)	
On the Reliability and Validity of Detecting Approval of Political Actors in Tweets Indira Sen, Fabian Floeck, and Claudia Wagner. Conference on Empirical Methods on Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)	2020
Empowering First Responders through Automated Multimodal Content Moderation DIVAM GUPTA, INDIRA SEN, NIHARIKA SACHDEVA, PONNURANGAM KUMARAGURU, ARUN BALAJI BUDURU. IEEE International Conference on Cognitive Computing	<b>2018</b> Best Paper Award
Worth its Weight in Likes: Towards Detecting Fake Likes on Instagram Indira Sen, Anupama Aggarwal, Shiven Mian, Siddharth Singh, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru, Anwitaman Datta. WebSci	2018 short paper
Workshop Articles	
What Human Rationales Tell us about Machine Explanations Indira Sen, Mattia Samory, Fabian Floeck, Claudia Wagner HCI+NLP Workshop, In conjunction with EACL	2021
Measuring Public Opinion Online: Potentials and Pitfalls	2020
INDIRA SEN, FABIAN FLOECK, CLAUDIA WAGNER WOMEN IN MACHINE LEARNING (WIML), IN CONJUNCTION WITH NEURIPS	Poster
A Twitter Corpus for Hindi-English Code Mixed POS Tagging	2018
Kushagra Singh, <b>Indira Sen</b> , Ponnurangam Kumaraguru. Workshop on Natural Language Processing for Social Media (SocialNLP), In conjunction with ACL	Data Paper
Language Identification and Named Entity Recognition in Hinglish Code Mixed Tweets Kushagra Singh, Indira Sen, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru. ACL Student Research Workshop	2018
Experience	
Snap Inc.	Santa Monica, USA

Jul 2022 - Oct 2022

RESEARCH INTERN, COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENCE. ADVISOR: DR. FRANCESCO BARBIERI

• Developing a Stakeholder-centred Framework for Multilingual Sensitive Content Detection

Nokia Bell Labs Cambridge, UK (virtual)

INTERN AT SOCIAL DYNAMICS GROUP. ADVISOR: DR. DANIELE QUERCIA

Jun 2021 - Aug 2021

- · Understanding and Characterizing the sustainability efforts of companies from employee reviews.
- Developed mixed-method techniques for detecting employees' views on their employer's sustainability efforts using a deep-learning framework (SBERT)
- Results from the internship were published at CSCW'22 and IEEE Vis'22.

SAGE Ocean London, UK (virtual)

SAGE OCEAN FELLOW. ADVISOR: DR. DANIELA DUCA

Oct 2020 - Dec 2020

- Contributing to a Text cleaning WebApp called Texti
- · Working on NLP transformations in Python and documentation
- · Results from the Fellowship are described here.

#### **Computational Social Science Department, GESIS**

Cologne, Germany

Doctoral Researcher. Advisors: Prof. Claudia Wagner, Dr. Katrin Weller

Oct 2018 - Present

- · Identifying, Characterizing and Quantifying errors that occur when measuring attitudes from Digital Traces
- · Building robust and interpretable NLP methods for measuring social science phenomena
- Large scale Twitter data collection using Amazon Web Services (AWS) as a service for Social Scientists.

#### Precog Research Lab, IIIT Delhi

New Delhi, India

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE. ADVISORS: PROF. PONNURANGAM KUMARAGURU AND PROF. ARUN BALAJI BUDURU

Dec 2017 - Aug 2018

- Landscaping the fake like marketplace on Instagram and characterizing fake likers, and their attack vectors.
- Detecting Multimodal Hatespeech on Social Media

#### CHILI Lab, École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland

SUMMER INTERN, ADVISOR: PROF. PIERRE DILLENBOURG

Jun 2017– Aug 2017

• Worked on inferring dependencies between EPFL courses based on Concept Mining and grading patterns

#### **Nanyang Technological University**

Singapore

RESEARCH ASSISTANT, ADVISOR: PROF. ANWITAMAN DUTTA

Jan 2017– May 2017

• Master's Thesis: Worked on detecting fake engagement on Instagram.

# **Teaching, Mentorship, and Academic Service**

#### Translation Tutorial on the Total Error Paradigm for Social Inferences

Barcelona, Spain

FAT\* 2020

Jan 2020

• Tutorial on diagnosing errors and biases in observational studies from digital traces

#### Introduction to Python and Data Science with Python

Cologne, Germany

University of Cologne

Oct, 2019

· Interactive, hands-on five-day lecture series for teaching introductory python concepts to social science doctoral candidates

#### Mentorship

SUPERVISED ON CO-SUPERVISED THESES

- Esi Doda (RWTH Aachen). Master's Thesis. Racial Disparities in Social Media Commentary about Football
- Vani Agarwal (IIIT-D). Master's Thesis. Improving Content Moderation through Co-Training
- Kushagra Singh (IIIT-D). Bachelor's Thesis. Information Extraction Tools for Code-Mixed Hindi-English Social Media Content

#### **PC** member

WEBCONF (2023), ICWSM (2021, 2022), ACL STUDENT RESEARCH WORKSHOP (2020, 2021, 2022), WIKIWORKSHOP (2022), HCI+NLP WORKSHOP (2022)

#### Reviewer

CSCW (2019, 2020), THEWEBCONF (2020, 2021), EMNLP (2020), ACL ROLLING REVIEW (2021, 2022), EPJ DATA SCIENCE (2022)

## Skills\_

Programming: Python, R, Java, C++, C, MongoDB, SQL, Bash

**Libraries/Tools:** scikit-learn, pytorch, tensorflow, huggingface, keras, pandas, NLTK, NetworkX, Amazon Web Services, Amazon Mechanical Turk, Prolific, Qualtrics

July 11, 2023 Indira Sen · CV